Andy Galpin: What do we actually know
about sleep differences
between men and women?
What I actually want
to know about is chromosomally.
When you tease out the hormones,
whether it's a polymorphism
or some other activity
at the level of the genome,
how is that actually manipulating,
manifesting itself into sleep?
Any idea what mechanisms would possibly be
there if it's not endocrine?
Allison Brager: In terms
of mechanism of action,
we know, again,
there's differences in sleep pressure.
If you unpack the onion,
sleep pressure is manifest
from increasing levels
of extracellular adenosine production
within the brain,
particularly the basal forebrain,
which is a wake-promoting area.
If sleep pressure is accumulating quickly,
which seems to be the case
in biological males
by way of the testes-determining gene,
then there's more rapid accumulation
of extracellular adenosine,
and the only way to pay off
that increasing sleep pressure
is through daytime sleep.
With females, it just essentially means
the rate of accumulation
of sleep pressure is lower,
which means that the production
of extracellular adenosine
would be lower.
Now, whether that's been studied,
it hasn't, but hypothetically,
just knowing
with all the myriad of studies
around accumulating sleep pressure
and extracellular adenosine,
we predict that's
the mechanism of action.
Andy: That's the closest
we can come at this point, right?
Allison: Right.
Andy: Is it fair?
Is it a trope?
I certainly know
that it feels like the guys
that I know versus the girls that I know,
guys fall asleep fast.
Allison: Oh, yes.
Andy: Is that actually been demonstrated?
Do we know that?
Allison: Yes. That's been
demonstrated, again,
in these preclinical
transgenic mouse models
using the four-core genotype.
It's also been demonstrated
in human studies.
In those studies that were done
in the '80s by Terry Lee
and Rachel Manber,
that's exactly what they found
is sleep onset for men
is much quicker.
Then when you look at time
to restorative sleep,
so that entry into stage 3 non-REM
and then REM sleep,
the latency is quicker for females.
It might take them longer to fall asleep,
but to get that restorative sleep,
it's much quicker
and then much more efficient
across the night.
Andy: Do we have any teleological
or evolutionary guess as to why
that setup is there?
Allison: I think it all goes
back to child-rearing, right?
Who's responsible for children?
Men are responsible
for propagating children,
but women,
they are the caretakers.
I think these are these
built-in neurochemical,
neuroanatomical circuits
that exist because of relationships
between who actually
takes care of the child.
Andy: How much of it is,
if you know, psychology
versus biology there?
The classic thing
you'll hear is like,
"Oh, women ruminate more.
They think about stuff more.
They're paying attention,"
or is it simply any host of cascades
haven't kicked off yet?
The pressure isn't high enough.
Do we have any idea of what--
I'm sure it's both are contributing.
Allison: I think
that's the psychological aspect,
from my lens,
is a part of that biological blueprint.
It's because females are going
to have greater vigilance
across the day.
What neurochemically is vigilance?
It's increased acetylcholine release
and activation
of acetylcholine areas of the brain,
like the basal forebrain,
that are going to lead to that.
Again, I see the world
from the lens of nature versus nurture.
I'm not a very good colleague
in departments of psychology.
Andy: You have a degree in psychology.
Allison: I have
an undergraduate degree in psychology,
but really-
Andy: Neuroscience.
Allison: -it's all neuroscience.
I was fortunate enough that I did go
to a university that really thrived
on its neuroscience curriculum.
Andy: Nonetheless,
I heard you're a psychologist,
and what I just heard you
say was psychology
is just misunderstood physiology.
I get it.
That's what you said.
Allison: I agree.
Yes, it is. [laughs]
Andy: Dr. Brager said it.
Hold my stamp to that.
Acetylcholine,
is that a total concentration issue
that generally is higher,
or is it a receptor density,
or is it both?
Do we have any idea of what are actually
the sex differences between acetylcholine?
Allison: That's a good question.
The studies that I know exist
on sex differences
focus on one particular area,
which is the basal forebrain.
That is the seat
of major acetylcholinergic production
and release and activation
within the brain.
Then there's cascading
effects on other areas.
No, I actually think this is
the land of great unknown.
There haven't been a lot of studies
on sex differences
and physiology and behavior.
If there were, they were done again
in the '80s and '90s-
Andy: Totally.
Allison: You got me curious
about going back
onto PubMed and Google Scholar
and looking this up.
Andy: I mean, the stuff
that has been done since then,
a lot of it is questionnaires.
It is.
It's pretty low-fidelity stuff,
which is good and helpful.
Allison: You need self-report.
With our sleep studies
that we do in humans now,
we always have
an objective endpoint endocrine
or even behavioral cognitive measure,
but it's always paired with self-report.
Sometimes the self-report data
is what lends
the more interesting findings.
Andy: Women, men fall asleep differently.
We get that. What about total duration
and waking-up time?
Any sex differences
that are notable there?
Allison: I'm happy you asked
that because I feel like that data
has been taken a little bit too far
on social media that women need
more sleep than men.
There is a difference in total sleep time
between men and women that was found again
in these studies in the 1980s,
and it's about 25 minutes
to 30 minutes different.
I come from this lens,
is that clinically significant?
I can't answer that,
but I feel like in social media
that people have taken that information
and have run with it that women
need to spend--
I think I saw something recently
like because women take
this long to fall asleep,
they need to be in bed for nine
and a half hours versus a guy
who falls asleep quickly,
they only need to be in bed for eight.
I think, at a certain point,
that's just going to create
anxiety around the act of sleeping
that it's going to be more harmful
than helpful.
Andy: I assume then also,
based on this men nap more
than women do.
Allison: Yes, we know that.
We know that experimentally,
we know that anecdotally,
you just look at cultures around
the world that have siestas
and/or it's adopted
and celebrated that people nap
during the day,
as we know that men
in general across cultures
are more prone to daytime sleepiness
and transgenic mice too.
Andy: Yes, name there.
Are people napping more or less
or the same than we have historically?
Allison: That, I don't know.
I feel like,
at least in the last 10 years,
that stigma around napping
has been reduced,
I would say.
It still exists in the military.
Andy: Of course.
Allison: I don't think it's going away.
Actually, my colleagues
and I from Walter Reed,
we have a paper that we published
in the flagship journal of sleep around--
it's called The Stigma
of Workplace Napping.
We strategically anonymously took quotes
from senior leaders in the military,
and we were flabbergasted.
They were like, "No, if my employees nap,
they're lazy.
They're not productive."
I'm like,
"Okay.
Just whatever."
[chuckles]
Andy: If you enjoyed this clip,
you can watch the full episode
by clicking here.
[music]